A Finding Aid to the Gabriella De Ferrari Papers, 1931-2011, bulk 1975-2011, in the Archives of American Art AAA.defemari
Archives of American Art
Gabriella De Ferrari papers
bulk 1975-2011
1931-2011
AAA.defemari
Archives of American Art
7.7 Linear feet
The papers of art historian Gabriella De Ferrari measure 7.7 linear feet and date from 1931-2011, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1975-2011. The collection provides an overview of her activities as an arts administrator, writer, and philanthropist through biographical materials, correspondence, interviews, extensive writings and notes, subject files, printed material, scrapbooks, and photographs.
De Ferrari, Gabriella
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1947-2003 (Boxes 1, 9; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1964-2011 (Boxes 1-2; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Interviews, 1990-1996 (Box 2; 3 folders)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1950-2010 (Boxes 3-6; 3.6 linear feet)
Series 5: Subject Files, 1953-2008 (Boxes 6-7; 1 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1961-2011 (Box 7; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, 1974-1981 (Box 9; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1931-circa 2010 (Box 8, 0.4 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
Art historian Gabriella De Ferrari (1941-) has lived and worked in Boston, Massachusetts and New York City.
Born in Tacna, Peru to Italian parents, De Ferrari graduated with a Bachelor of Arts from Saint Louis University in Missouri in 1963. She went on to receive a Master of Arts from the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University in 1966, and in 1981, she earned a Masters of Art in Fine Arts from Harvard University. De Ferrari has held administrative and curatorial positions at major museums and art organizations. At the Institute of Contemporary Art, Boston, she was curator of exhibitions before becoming the Director of the Institute in 1975. From 1978-1982, De Ferrari was Assistant Director of Curatorial Affairs and Programs at the Fogg Museum and the Busch-Reisinger Museum, where her responsibilities included exhibition programs for twentieth century art and coordinating programs for corporate and public fundraising. In 1989, De Ferrari moved to New York City, where she established herself as a freelance writer. In 1990, her novel, A Cloud on Sand received a Barnes and Noble Discover Award. Gringa Latina, De Ferrari's memoir about her experience living in two cultures was published in 1994.
She has served on the Boards of Trustees and on the advisory committees of many leading institutions, including Colby College, City University Graduate Center Foundation, Harvard University Museum, the New School, and the Wadsworth Atheneum. From 2000-2006, she was the philanthropic advisor to the chairman and CEO of United Technologies Corporation. In 1996, De Ferrari was awarded the New School Medal for Distinguished Service, and in 2008, she received an Honorary Doctorate in Letters from Colby College.
Gabriella De Ferrari continues to reside in New York City.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Gabriella De Ferrari, in 2011.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of art historian Gabriella De Ferrari measure 7.7 linear feet and date from 1931-2011, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1975-2011. The collection provides an overview of her activities as an arts administrator, writer, and a philanthropist through biographical materials, correspondence, interviews, extensive writings and notes, subject files, printed material, scrapbooks, and photographs.
Correspondence with artists, academic administrators, museum directors, curators, literary agents, editors, and publishers is primarily of a social nature, e.g., thank you notes, invitations, and congratulatory letters. Letters include references to De Ferrari's professional activities from circa 1975-circa 2006. There are illustrated letters and handmade birthday cards by De Ferrari, family, and friends. Among the correspondents are Michael Brenson, James Cuno, Francine Du Plessix Gray, Agnes Gund, Alex and Ada Katz, Sol and Carol Lewitt, and Glen Seator.
Writings and notes primarily document Gabriella De Ferrari's career as an author and include numerous drafts and annotated versions of her novels, short stories, memoir, and articles. Subject files include materials chronicling De Ferrari's activities at the Busch-Reisinger Museum, the Institute of Contemporary Art in Boston, and the Pan-American Society of New England. Also documented is her service as a Board of Trustees member, consultant, and advisor to major educational, corporate, and cultural institutions, including the New School University, United Technologies, Inc., and the Wadsworth Atheneum, among others. Interviews of De Ferrari are found on six sound cassettes. Additional audio cassettes and one videocassette are found within her writings.
Photographs are of Gabriella De Ferrari, family members, friends, and colleagues, including Michael Brenson, Leo Castelli, Agnes Gund, Martin Segal, Ingrid Sischy, Sol Lewitt, among others.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Busch-Reisinger Museum.; Castelli, Leo; Cuno, James B.; Gray, Francine du Plessix; Gund, Agnes; Institute of Contemporary Art (Boston, Mass.).; Katz, Ada, 1928-; Katz, Alex, 1927-; LeWitt, Carol; LeWitt, Sol, 1928-2007; Michael, Brenson; New School University; Pan-American Society of New England.; Seator, Glen; Segal, Martin; Sischy, Ingrid; Wadsworth Atheneum; Art historians--Massachusetts--Boston; Art historians--New York (State)--New York; Arts administrators--Massachusetts--Boston; Arts administrators--New York (State)--New York; Authors--Massachusetts; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Diaries; Illustrated letters; Interviews; Philanthropists--Massachusetts--Boston; Philanthropists--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings
- Biographical Material, 1947-2003; Series 1; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 1, 9
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material chronicles Gabriella De Ferrari's career as an arts administrator and a freelance writer through curriculum vitae, educational records, and letters of appointment. Educational records contain diplomas from St. Louis University, the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University, and Harvard University. Also found is a transcript from the Faculty of Arts and Sciences, Harvard University and a photograph of De Ferrari at her college graduation. A communion album and two autograph albums document De Ferrari's life growing up in Tacna, Peru and later as a young woman studying at Marymount International School in London, England. A file on De Ferrari's daughter, Gabriella Brignole Jeppson includes a birth certificate and a handmade booklet. Other biographical information includes passports and miscellaneous materials, e.g., an awards program, a certificate of achievement from the Marquis Who's Who Publications Board, an identification badge from the Harvard University Art Museums, a New York City voting registration card, and scattered calling cards.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by subject.
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1981-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Educational Records - Diplomas and Transcript, 1963-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9
  - Letters of Appointment, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Passports, 1983-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Communion Album, 1979; 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Autograph Albums, 1947-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gabriella Brignole Jeppson, 1973; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Materials, circa 1962-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oversized Educational Records - Diplomas and Transcript from Box 1, Folder 4, 1981 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, 1964-2011; Series 2; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence references De Ferrari's varied career as an arts administrator, curator, writer, and as an philanthropic advisor to educational and cultural institutions. Included are a number of letters pertaining to De Ferrari's donations of artwork to museums and other institutions, such as Harvard University Art Museums, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Museum of Modern Art (New York), and the New School University.
  Correspondence, for the most part, is arranged in alphabetical order and filed chronologically thereafter. All correspondents with 5 or more letters associated with their name are housed in a named file. "Unidentified correspondents" at the end of the named files are filed by their forename or the first letter of their forename. Remaining files are letters with unintelligible signatures or unsigned. Also found are two computer disks of De Ferrari's letters.
  - A, 1976-2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - B, circa 1970-2009 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Baxter, Douglas, 2001-2005 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brenson, Michael, 1997-2003 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brignole, Domingo, 1982-2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - C, circa 1970-2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Casteleiro, Manuel F., circa 1999 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Colby College, 1999-2008 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Creative Time, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - D, circa 1970-2007 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - David, George and Marie Douglas David, circa 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - De Ferrari, Gabriella, 1997-2008 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Doran, Happy, circa 1980-2009 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - E-F, circa 1980-2009 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Fanton, Jonathan, 1988-circa 2005 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Farley, Katherine, circa 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fogg Museum, 1976-2003 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - G, 1975-2007 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gray, Francine Du Plessix, circa 1990-2004 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gund, Agnes, 1981-2009 (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - H, 1974-2011 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Harvard University Art Museums, 1985-2011 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - I, 1973-2006 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - J-K, circa 1970-2010 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Jeppson, Gabriella, circa 1980-2008 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Jeppson, Nathaniel, circa 1970-2005 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - L, 1964-2008 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Lauder, Ronald and Carole Jo Lauder, circa 1990-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lewitt, Sol and Carol, 1998-2007 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - M, 1975-2011 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 2003-2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Montoya, Manuel, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mowry, Robert, 2002-2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Museum of Modern Art (New York), 1995-2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - N, 1976-2009 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - New School University, 1996-2011 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Novograd, Nancy, circa 1990-circa 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - O, circa 2000-2005 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - P-Q, 1975-2006 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - R, 1975-2005 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - S, 1976-2009 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Segal, Martin, 1980-2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - T-V, 1970-circa 2011 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - United Technologies Corporation, 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - W-Y, 1975-2010 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified (First Names Only) (Box 2)
    - A-B, circa 1970-2010 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - C-D, circa 1974-2005 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - E-F, circa 1970-2004 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - G-H, circa 1980-2004 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - I-J, circa 1977-2005 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - K, circa 1990-2006 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - L-M, 1968-2007 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - N,P, circa 1970-2010 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - R, circa 1990-2007 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - S-T, circa 1974-circa 2010 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - W, 1998-2002 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Illegible, undated; circa 1975-2004 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - Correspondence, circa 1980-circa 2000; 2 Floppy discs (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Interviews, 1990-1996; Series 3; 3 Folders Box 2
  This series includes sound recordings of three interviews with Gabriella De Ferrari.
  Interviews are arranged in chronological order.
  - Interview with Gabriella De Ferrari conducted by unidentified interviewer, 1990; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Interviews with Gabriella De Ferrari conducted by Verlyn Klinkenborg, 1995; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Interview with Gabriella De Ferrari conducted by Pat Beard, 1996; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Writings and Notes, 1950-2010; Series 4; 3.6 Linear feet Boxes 3-6
  The bulk of the writings by Gabriella De Ferrari consist of drafts, annotated manuscript versions, and page proofs of De Ferrari's A Cloud on Sand (Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1990) and Gringa Latina: A Woman of Two Worlds (Houghton Mifflin, 1994). Files include editors' query letters, memoranda, a letter of intent and a publishing agreement, publicity-related material, an outline for a film adaptation, and photographic reproduction of dust cover jacket. Found is an audiobook on cassette of A Cloud on Sand. Drafts of articles written for major publications, such as Connoisseur, Mirabella, and Travel + Leisure include De Ferrari's profiles on artists and other art world figures, such as Georg Baselitz, Sol Lewitt, and Vera List, as well as articles on travel, fashion, and book reviews.
  There is a sound recording of De Ferrari reading at the New York Public Library and one videocassette of a lecture at an unidentified venue. Thirty-one notebooks contain De Ferrari's notes for books, interviews, and articles. Twenty-nine appointment books record personal and professional engagements from 1969-2005. Also found are fifty-two 3.5" floppy discs of drafts of her writings.
  Writings by others consist of a screenplay of A Cloud On Sand by Arthur Hopcraft and a talk, "The Curator's Moment: A Commentary on the Bellagio Conference on International Exhibitions" by Michael Brenson.
  This series is arranged as two subseries.
  4.1: Writings and Notes by Gabriella De Ferrari, 1950-2010
  4.2: Writings and Notes by Others, 1991, 1997
  - Writings and Notes by Gabriella De Ferrari, 1950-2010; 4.1
    - Novels (Box 3)
      - A Cloud on Sand, Annotated Manuscript Version, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - A Cloud on Sand, Last Revised Version, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
      - A Cloud on Sand, Notes, circa 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - A Cloud on Sand, Audiobook, 1990; 9 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Reason in the Storm, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
      - Gringa Latina, Draft, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Gringa Latina, Annotated Manuscript Versions, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 12-18)
      - Gringa Latina, Annotated Manuscript Versions, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      - Gringa Latina, Author Set Pages, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
      - Gringa Latina, Published Version, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
      - Diver, 1992-1997 (Box 4, Folder 9-13)
      - Don Illario Cambiasso or The Color of Silence, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
    - Short Stories (Box 4)
      - "A Man of Small Volume", 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
      - "About His Love for Piero", 1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - "After His Death", 1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - "A House", 1997-2000 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "Moon Mountain", circa 1997 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "My Clone", 1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - "Stone, Sand, and Water", 1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - "Two Flowers: An Inca Tale", 1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Short Stories - Notes, circa 1997; 1988 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Other Writings (Box 5)
      - Personal Essays, 1990-1997 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
      - On the Art World, circa 1980-circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Student Papers, circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Magazine Articles, 1991-2007 (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
      - Drafts of Talks, 1997-2003 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Reading at New York Public Library, 1995; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Lecture, 1995; 1 Videocassettes (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Student Notebooks, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
      - Recipe Notebook, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Notes for Novels, 1989-circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Research Notes, 1989-2006 (Box 5, Folder 22-28)
      - Lists, 1980-2005; undated (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
      - Appointment Books, 1969-2005 (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
    - Writings and Notes, 1988-1999; 52 Floppy discs (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
  - Writings and Notes by Others, 1991; 1997; 4.2
    - By Arthur Hopcroft, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - By Michael Brenson, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Subject Files, 1953-2008; Series 5; 1 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  This series documents Gabriella De Ferrari's career as an arts administrator and writer. Files contain a variety of material, including draft versions of manuscripts, memoranda, a search committee report, source materials, a loan agreement, a list of artwork, author/publisher contracts, guest lists, speeches, and photographs. Among the printed materials are press releases, newsletters, exhibition invitations, brochures, clippings, and photographs.
  This series includes files for several exhibitions organized under the direction of De Ferrari including "Joan Snyder and Pat Steir" and "A Selection of American Art: The Skowhegan School" at the Institute of Contemporary Art; and "Prints of Anders Zorn" and "75 Years of Collecting" at the Busch-Reisinger Museum. There is a file on Gabriella De Ferrari's role in developing the Colby College Museum's contemporary art collection; also included is a draft of her speech on receiving an honorary doctorate from the college.
  This series is arranged by subject.
  - A Cloud on Sand, 1983-1995 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Boston Review, Drafts of Articles, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Colby College, 1998-2008 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Corporate Philanthropy/the Arts, 2003-2006 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Creative Time, 2003-2005 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Cultural Identity and the New Immigrant, 1988-2003 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Laura De Ferrari, 1990-1994 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Eggplant Project, 1960-1991 (Box 6, Folder 22-26)
  - Galleries, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Harvard University Art Museums, 1978-2008 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Harvard University, John F. Kennedy School of Government, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - House and Garden, 1991-1996 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Institute of Contemporary Art, 1974-1977 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Kentler International Drawing Space, 2003-2004 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mary Miss, 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - New School University, 1992-2005 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - New York Times, 2002-2004; 1953 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Pan-American Society, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Potatoes, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Umbrellas, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1999-2003 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, 1961-2011; Series 6; 0.8 Linear feet Box 7
  The series primarily contains newspaper and magazine clippings documenting De Ferrari's career. Included are clippings of two op-ed pieces by De Ferrari, including a piece on the September 11, 2001 attacks and one on private art in public spaces that appeared in the New York Times.
  A large portion of the series includes clippings of De Ferrari's articles for major publications, including Architectural Digest and Vanity Fair, among others. Also found are reviews of De Ferrari's novel and memoir; scattered among these clippings are press releases and publishers' brochures. Some of the reviews are in Spanish. Files include materials relating to exhibitions. The catalog for the exhibition "Drawn from a Family: Contemporary Works on Paper" held at Colby College reflects the art collecting interests of De Ferrari and her family.
  Among the miscellaneous printed materials are press types, brochures, and travel itineraries.
  This series is arranged by format.
  - Press Releases, 1995; 2005 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters, 1974-2003 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Catalogs, 1973-1997 (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
  - Announcements, 1990-2005 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Invitations, 1982; 1998-2011 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Programs, 1979-2004 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - News Clippings - Book Reviews, 1990-1995 (Box 7, Folder 20-21)
  - Other News Clippings, 1961-2005 (Box 7, Folder 22-23)
  - Magazine Clippings - Articles by Gabriella De Ferrrari, 1987-2008 (Box 7, Folder 24-26)
  - Magazine Clippings - Book Reviews, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Other Magazine Clippings, 1978-circa 2000 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Reproductions - Postcards, 1999; undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1990-2009; undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
- Scrapbooks, 1974-1981; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 9
  This series provides an overview of the exhibitions organized or curated by Gabriella De Ferrari at the Institute of Contemporary Arts in Boston, the Busch-Reisinger Museum and the Fogg Museum. Materials contain mostly fundraising letters, press releases, newsletters, invitations and announcements, clippings, exhibition itineraries, drawings, and photographs.
  Scrapbooks are arranged in chronological order.
  - Oversized Scrapbook 1, 1974-1980 (Box 9)
  - Oversized Scrapbook 2, 1976-1981 (Box 9)
- Photographs, 1931-circa 2010; Series 8; 0.4 Linear feet Box 8
  Photographs are of Gabriella De Ferrari with family members, colleagues, and friends. Photographs are of De Ferrari as a child and youth growing up in Tacna, Peru and at school in England. Included are snapshots of De Ferrari with her parents and sister. There are black and white portrait photographs of De Ferrari, many of them done for publicity purposes. Snapshots of De Ferrari with her family, friends, and colleagues were taken at professional gatherings, while traveling, or at home. There are snapshots of book parties held for De Ferrari by Martin Segal, Agnes Gund, and others, upon the publication of A Cloud on Sand and Gringa Latina. One snapshot features Agnes Gund with Sol Lewitt and Martin Segal. Most of the individuals and venues in the photographs are unidentified.
  Other photographs are of Gabriella's residences in New York City and Connecticut. Also found are black and white photos of views of Genoa, Italy, the home of the De Ferrari family.
  - Gabriella De Ferrari, 1949-1996 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - Gabriella De Ferrari with Family and Friends, circa 1990-circa 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - Family and Friends, circa 1942-2004 (Box 8, Folder 6-10)
  - Photographs of Book Parties, 1990-1995 (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1998-circa 2001; circa 1931 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Interior Views - Gabriella De Ferrari's Residences, 1996-circa 2010 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Scattered Exterior Views - Cityscapes and Landscapes, 1976-1996; 1931 (Box 8, Folder 15)